Guide to the Armenian Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1975-2011 UA.40.20.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Armenian Nationality Room Committee Collection
1975-2011
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Armenian Nationality Room Committee
UA.40.20.04
5.5 Linear Feet (6) Boxes
The Armenian Nationality Room Collection holds records documenting the planning, design, funding, construction, and promotion of the Armenian Nationality Room in the University of Pittsburgh's Nationality Rooms Program at the Cathedral of Learning. The majority of the collection was originally assembled by Charles Klanian and later donated to the Nationality Rooms Program Office, while a 2001 deposit was originally housed and maintained by the Programs Office.
Accruals
Further accruals are expected from the activities of the Committee.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Planning
Series II. Design and Construction
Series III. Active Use
Series IV: Oversized Records
Series V: Multimedia
Series IV. 2001 Deposit
History
Dedicated on August 28, 1988, the Armenian Nationality Room (ANR) took ten years to design, fund, and construct. It is located on the third floor of the Cathedral of Learning and is the twenty-first Nationality Classroom completed. Charles Klanian, Chairman of the Armenian Nationality Room Committee was the driving force behind the formation of the Armenian Nationality Committee. It began with the incorporation of the Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh in 1977 whose purpose was to raise funds for the construction and maintenance of the room.
Due to the small size of the Armenian community in Pittsburgh, funding issues delayed the building of the classroom until notable donations by David and Lois Shakarian, and Alex and Marie Mangooian were secured. Torkom Khrimian, a Los Angeles architect, was contracted to complete the design of the classroom. Eugene V. Dotter was established as Engineer of the Record, and James Gerald as Associate Architect. John Deklewa & Sons, Inc. was selected as the project's contractor.
The Matenadran (library) at the Sanahin Monastery in Northern Armenia became the major design inspiration for the ANR. Columns supporting the ceiling and dome, a yertik (octagonal opening in the dome), and stone masonry were major components incorporated into construction and drawn from Armenian architectural tradition. The final design emulates 10th and 12th century Armenian architecture and was constructed of 22 tons of steel and Indiana limestone. Other features include the carved wood furniture, inscribed walls in Armenian script, wrought iron decorations, and replicated and authentic cultural artifacts. The goal of the committe was to create a public space that supported the visibility of the Armenian community in Pittsburgh and showcased the cultural and intellectual achievements of all Armenians.
Existence and Location of Copies
Video and audio materials of the collection have copies located in the Nationality Rooms Program office.
Acquisition Information
The Armenian Nationality Room Collection was created by Charles Klanian, previous Chairman for the Armenian Nationality Room Committee, and donated to the Nationality Rooms Program office by Klanian heirs after his death. In accordance with preserving activities of each classroom on the Nationality Council, the records were collected and maintained by the Nationality Rooms Program staff.
Previous Citation
Armenian Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1975-2011, UA.40.20.04, University of Pittsburgh Archives
Scope and Content Notes
The Armenian Nationality Room collection holds records documenting the planning, designing, funding, creating, and promoting of the Armenian Nationality Room in the University of Pittsburgh's Nationality Rooms Program at the Cathedral of Learning. The majority of the collection was originally assembled by Charles Klanian and later donated to the Nationality Rooms Program Office, while a 2001 deposit was originally housed and maintained by the Programs Office.
The collection is arranged by series and subseries. There are six series in total. The first series is composed of records from the Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh Foundation, which shows the beginning plans for the Armenian Nationality Room and Committee. These records include progress reports, event documentation, expense reports, travel expense notebooks, fundraising and donation notices, member and donor information, community news, research materials, and a documentation of a trip to Armenia during the years 1975 to 1985. The second series is composed of records from the years 1986-1988; those records contain information about progress reports, events, expense reports, travel expenses, fundraising and donations, member and donor information, research, the final design of the classroom, and publicity, plans for a dedication book, and records of the room dedication. The third series has records of progress reports, events, travel expenses, fundraising and donations, member and donor information, publicity, and room additions made in the years 1989 to 2011. The fourth series is composed of oversized design and architectural records that had to be physically separated from the rest of the collection. The fifth series contains visual and audio multimedia: slides, photographs, contact sheets, negatives, photographic prints, 3/4" umatic video tape, VHS tape, audio cassette tape, and 1/4" audio tape.
The last series, Series VI, holds the 2001 Collection which is composed of Armenian Nationality Room records that were developed into a collection by the Nationality Rooms Program staff members in 2001.This 2001 Collection is composed entirely of papers relating to the Armenian Nationality Classroom generated by, or sent to, the Nationality Rooms Program office. Researchers should note these is a more complete account of room events hosted by the Armenian Nationality Room Committee in this series.
Minutes (Administrative records); Video recordings (physical artifacts); Sound recordings; Photographs; Financial records; Correspondence; Architectural drawings (Visual works); Armenians -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Armenian Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Classrooms -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Armenian Nationality Room Committee; Nationality Rooms (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.); Klanian, Charles S.; Shakarian, David; Mangooian, Alex; Bruhns, E. Maxine; Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh (Pa.); Armenian Nationality Classroom (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa); University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program
- Planning, 1975-1985; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains information about the creation of the Armenian Nationality Room through the Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh. It contains materials from 1975 to 1985: progress reports, event documentation, expense reports, travel expense notebooks, fundraising and donation notices, member and donor information, community news, research materials, and documentation of a trip to Armenia.
  - Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh Foundation, 1977-1981; 1.
    This subseries contains reports on activities, meeting minutes, correspondence, notices, planning the creation of the Armenian Nationality Room, quarterly treasurer reports, donor forms, event planning, expense reports, and status reports relating to talent search for architecture and room decoration.
    - Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh Foundation, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      This folder contains the seal of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, articles of confederation, and the Armenian-American Club by-laws.
    - Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh Foundation, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh Foundation, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh Foundation, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Progress Reports, 1978-1985; 2.
    This subseries contains materials relating to the progress on the planning, construction, decoration, and dedication of the Armenian Nationality Room. This includes preliminary designs, design drawers, design review criteria, records establishing the quasi-endowment fund, theme notes, meeting minutes, member lists, correspondence, university pledges, newsletters, letters to board members, designer records, and presentation notes.
    - Progress Reports, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
    - Progress Reports, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Progress Reports, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Progress Reports, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
      Folder 11 contains the Construction Bid for the Armenian Nationality Room.
    - Progress Reports, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Progress Reports, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15-19)
      Folder 16 contains the CSK 21885 Agreement between the Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh and Torkom Khrimian the Armenian Nationality Room's architect and designer. Folder 19 contains the preliminary design of the Armenian Nationality Room.
  - Events, 1979-1983; 3.
    The subseries contains records relating to events hosted by the Armenian Nationality Room Committee. These events include speakers, symposiums, and banquets. These records include correspondence, handouts, personal notes, flyers, programs, speeches, press releases, newsletters, guest lists, and member lists.
    - Events, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Events, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Events, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Events, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - Events, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      This folder contains Charles Klanian's 1982 Martyr's Day speech.
  - Expense Reports, 1984-1985; 4.
    This subseries contains expense reports by the Armenian Nationality Room Committee relating to the years 1984 and 1985.
    - Expense Reports, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Travel Expenses, 1985; 5.
    This subseries contains travel expense notes from the Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh and the Armenian Nationality Room Committee for the year 1985.
    - Travel Expenses, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Fundraising and Donations, 1980-1985; 6.
    This subseries contains materials relating to fundraising and donations, including: correspondence, pamphlets, and treasurer memos.
    - Fundraising and Donations, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      This folder contains the treasurer memo to establish the quasi-endowment fund for the Armenian Nationality Room.
    - Fundraising and Donations, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Member and Donor Information, 1980-1984; 7.
    This subseries contains materials about significant publicity and information relating to individual members and donors of the Armenian Nationality Room. Notably, this includes Alex Manoogian, David Shakarian, and Papken Sassouni.
    - Member and Donor Information, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Member and Donor Information, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Community News, 1980, 1982-1983; 8.
    This subseries contains records retained by the Armenian Nationality Room relating to significant Armenian-American community news, historical publications relating to Armenians, and Armenian news. These records include published pamphlets, speech transcripts, reports, magazine articles, newspaper articles, and correspondence.
    - Community News, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Community News, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Research, 1975-1984; 9.
    This subseries contains research materials relating to the design of the Armenian Nationality Room. These materials include: magazine articles, book lists, correspondence, an architecture book, and design print outs.
    - Research, 1975-1984 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Armenian Trip, 1985; 10.
    This subseries contains record of the 1985 Armenian Nationality Room Armenian Trip. These records include correspondence, itineraries, letters of introduction, and an expense report.
    - Armenia Trip, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Design and Construction, 1986-1988; II.
  This series contains the materials from the Armenian Nationality Room in 1986-1988, much of it relating to the design, construction, and dedication of the room. The materials include: progress reports, event documentation, expense reports, travel expense notebooks, fundraising and donations notices, member and donor information, research materials, the final design packet, publicity records, papers concerning the dedication book, and dedication records. A majority of the subseries within this series are repeated three times to reflect the original, physical chronological arrangement by Charles Klanian.
  - Progress Reports, 1986; 1.
    This subseries contains meeting minutes, correspondence, notices, quarterly treasurer reports, stone masonry quotes, design drawings, a construction plan, structural calculations, electrical calculations, a maintenance agreement, construction costs lists, a donation plaque proposal, the beginning of the Shakarian escrow agreement, articles establishing the Armenian lecture series, two spiral-bound project specifications, and status reports on room progression.
    - Progress Reports, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 36-43)
      Folder 37 contains the Standard Form of Agreement between the University of Pittsburgh and Eugene V. Dotter Engineering, Inc. establishing Eugene V. Dotter as Engineer of the Record and James Gerald as Associate Architect.
    - Specifications for the Workmanship and Materials for the Construction of the Armenian Nationality Classroom, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
  - Events, 1986; 2.
    This subseries contains a record relating to Armenian Nationality Room event: a reception invitation list.
    - Events, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Expense Reports, 1986; 3.
    This subseries contains expense reports for the Armenian Nationality Room in the year 1986. This includes: checking account reports, income and expenses lists, cash reports, mailing receipts, and correspondence.
    - Expense Reports, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
  - Travel Expenses, 1986; 4.
    This subseries contains receipts, tickets, and notes relating to travel for members of the Armenian Room Committee in the year 1986.
    - Travel Expenses, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Fundraising and Donations, 1986; 5.
    This subseries contains records relating to donations and fundraising for the Armenian Nationality Room. This includes: correspondence, gift agreements, escrow agreements, and a copy of a check.
    - Fundraising and Donor Information, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
      Folder 50 contains records of the Alex and Marie Mangooian Foundation donation. Folder 51 contains the Lois Shakarian James escrow and gift agreement.
  - Member and Donor Information, 1986; 6.
    This subseries contains research materials about significant publicity and information relating to individual members and donors of the Armenian Nationality Room.
    - Member and Donor Information, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Research, 1986; 7.
    This subseries contains research materials relating to the design of the Armenian Nationality Room. These materials include: drawings and pictures of medieval Armenian churches.
    - Research, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Final Design, 1986; 8.
    This subseries contains materials relating to the final design of the Armenian Nationality Room Project. These materials include: correspondence, the final project report, electrical calculations, and structural calculations.
    - Final Design, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Publicity, 1986; 9.
    This subseries contains materials relating to publicity for the Armenian Nationality Room. These materials include: newspaper articles.
    - Publicity, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Progress Reports, 1987; 10.
    This subseries contains materials relating to the progression of the Armenian Nationality Room. These records are primarily concerned with building efforts and include: personal notes, correspondence, meeting minutes, speech transcripts, project meeting reports, schedules, design reviews, design sketches, invoices, weekly summaries, change orders copies, a contract agreement, reports to the Armenian-American Club of Pittsburgh, calculations, professional translations, architectural drawings, newsletters, and the General Conditions for the Contract of Construction booklet.
    - Progress Reports, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1-16)
      Folder 8 contains the Standard of Agreement between the University of Pittsburgh and a contractor: John Deklewa & Sons, Inc. Folder 14 contains design sketches of the door and furniture for the Armenian Nationality Room. Folder 15 contains design sketches of the door plaque for the Armenian Nationality Room.
  - Events, 1987; 11.
    This subseries contains records relating to Armenian Nationality Room events: an invitation list, speech transcripts, and correspondence.
    - Events, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Expense Reports, 1987; 12.
    This subseries contains expense reports for the Armenian Nationality Room in the year 1987. This includes cash reports, authorization forms, funding analysis, and checking account summaries.
    - Expense Reports, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
  - Travel Expenses, 1987; 13.
    This subseries contains receipts, tickets, and notes relating to travel for members of the Armenian Nationality Room Committee in 1987.
    - Travel Expenses, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Fundraising and Donations, 1987; 14.
    This subseries contains correspondence relating to fundraising efforts and donations for the Armenian Nationality Room in 1987.
    - Fundraising and Donations, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Publicity, 1987; 15.
    This subseries contains materials like press releases, correspondence, and newspaper articles relating to publicity for the Armenian Nationality Room in 1987.
    - Publicity, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Dedication Book, 1987; 16.
    This subseries contains materials relating to the creation of the Armenian Nationality Room dedication book: notes, drafts, correspondence, and copies of the dedication book.
    - Dedication Book, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Progress Reports, 1988; 17.
    This subseries contains records related to the progression of the formation and running of the Armenian Nationality Room. Records include: correspondence, surveys, funding notices, contractor reports, meeting minutes, programs, construction notes, speech transcripts, agenda lists, and project meeting reports.
    - Progress Reports, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 25-33)
  - Events, 1988; 18.
    This subseries contains records related to the Armenian Nationality Room events: lecture flyers, correspondence, and notes.
    - Events, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Expense Reports, 1988; 19.
    This subseries contains the 1988 expense reports for the Armenian Nationality Room. This includes materials like: correspondence, payment certifications, financial summaries, receipts, and cash reports.
    - Expense Reports, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 35-39)
  - Travel Expenses, 1988; 20.
    This subseries contains receipts, tickets, and notes relating to travel for members of the Armenian Nationality Room Committee in 1988.
    - Travel Expenses, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Fundraising and Donations, 1988; 21.
    This subseries contains correspondence relating to fundraising efforts and donations for the Armenian Nationality Room in 1988.
    - Fundraising and Donations, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
  - Community News, 1988; 22.
    This subseries contains records retained by the Armenian Nationality Room relating to significant Armenian-American community news, historical publications relating to Armenians, and Armenian news. These records include a press release, newspaper articles, and correspondence.
    - Community News, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Publicity, 1988; 23.
    This subseries contains materials like press releases, correspondence, magazine articles, newspaper articles, and the Nationality Rooms book relating to publicity for the Armenian Nationality Room in 1988.
    - Publicity, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
  - Dedication, 1988; 24.
    This subseries contains records of the Armenian Nationality Room's dedication on August 28, 1988. Records include: programs, invitations, pronunciation guides, flyers, banquet notices, correspondence, speech transcripts, and newspaper articles.
    - Dedication, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 46-48)
- Active Use, 1989-2011; III.
  This series contains materials from the Armenian Nationality Room in 1989-2011 concerning the continuation and the role of the Armenian Nationality Room and Committee in the Nationality Rooms Program. The materials include: progress reports, events, expense reports, fundraising and donation information, member and donor information, community news, publicity, and papers relating to room additions.
  - Progress Reports, 1989-2003; 1.
    This subseries contains progress reports of the Armenian Nationality Room from 1989 to 2003, materials include: correspondence, speeches, treasurer reports, council member lists, newsletters, emails, by-law amendments, donation lists, and funds reviews.
    - Progress Reports, 1989-1995 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      This folder contains two records translated from Armenian to English.
    - Progress Reports, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Progress Reports, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Progress Reports, 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Events, 1991-2002; 2.
    This subseries contains records relating to Armenian Nationality Room hosted events. These records include: correspondence, flyers, speeches, and agendas.
    - Events, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Events, 1993-2002 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Publicity, 1989-1993; 3.
    This subseries contains articles and publications promoting the Armenian Nationality Room.
    - Publicity, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Publicity, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Expense Reports, 1989-1991; 4.
    This subseries contains reports on Armenian Nationality Room expenses in the years 1989 to 1991.
    - Expense Reports, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fundraising and Donations, 1990-2001; 5.
    This subseries is composed of correspondence noting fundraising efforts and donations in the years 1990 to 2001.
    - Fundraising and Donations, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Member and Donor Information, 1989-2001; 6.
    This subseries has materials documenting notable correspondence and happenings to donors and members of the Armenian Nationality Room in 1989-2001.
    - Member and Donor Information, 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Member and Donor Information, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Member and Donor Information, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Community News, 1989-2001; 7.
    This subseries is composed of records of important events and news within the Armenian-American community.
    - Community News, 1989-2001 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Additions, 1989-2011; 8.
    This subseries contains photographs, correspondence, speeches, and personal notes relating to the acquisition of the katchkar (stone cross) and the addition of the wrought iron door hardware for the Armenian Nationality Room.
    - Katchkar, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Katchkar, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Wrought Iron Door Hardware, 2008-2011 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Oversized Records, 1987-1988; IV.
  This series is composed of oversized design and architectural records located in map case 26, drawer 1.
  - Architectural and Design Records, 1987-1988 (Map-case 26, Folder 1)
- Multimedia, 1982-2001; V.
  This series contains visual and audio multimedia: slides, photographs, contact sheets, negatives, photographic prints, 3/4" umatic video tape, VHS tape, audio cassette tape, and 1/4" audio tape.
  - Photographs, 1985-1995; 1.